<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Enormytees vsyd by the clergy here floweth dyuers enormytees vsyd by the clergy, and by some wryters theyr adherentis, and specyally agaynst the heresy of symony vsyd by the clergy : how some of the clergy and theyr adherentis causeles haue skla[n]derously spoken agayns this noble realme of Englande and agayns dyuers of the kynges lay subiectes, and haue prechyd &amp; wrytyn agaynst small offe[n]sys, leuyng ye greter offensys in the law of God vntouhcyd [sic].</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1532</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 44 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 25 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A00299</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 10421.5</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S2110</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">23035060</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 23035060</idno>
            <idno type="VID">26122</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A00299)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 26122)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1795:57)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Enormytees vsyd by the clergy here floweth dyuers enormytees vsyd by the clergy, and by some wryters theyr adherentis, and specyally agaynst the heresy of symony vsyd by the clergy : how some of the clergy and theyr adherentis causeles haue skla[n]derously spoken agayns this noble realme of Englande and agayns dyuers of the kynges lay subiectes, and haue prechyd &amp; wrytyn agaynst small offe[n]sys, leuyng ye greter offensys in the law of God vntouhcyd [sic].</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[46] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>John Skot,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[S.l. :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1532?]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Publisher from printer's mark at colophon.</note>
                  <note>Date of publication suggested by STC (2nd ed.).</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-C⁸ (last leaf blank).</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Trinity College (University of Cambridge). Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Church of England --  Clergy.</term>
               <term>Simony --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-10</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-10</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:26122:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:26122:1"/>
            <head>Enormytees vſyd by the Clergy.</head>
            <head>Here floweth dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers enormytees vſyd by the Clergy / and by ſome wryters theyr adherentis / and ſpecyally agaynſt the hereſy of ſymo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ny vſyd by the Clergy.</head>
            <div n="1" type="chapter">
               <head>¶How ſome of the Clergy and theyr adherentis cauſeles haue ſkla<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>derouſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly ſpoken agayns this noble realme of Englande and agayns dyuers of the Kynges lay ſubiectes / and haue prechyd &amp; wrytyn agaynſt ſmall offe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſys / leuyng y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> greter offenſys in the law of god vntouheyd. Ca. i.</head>
               <pb facs="tcp:26122:2"/>
               <p>THe grace of our lorde Ihu Chryſt / the charyte of god / and the comuny<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cacyon of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> holy goſte / be euer with our noble Kyng with his nobles &amp; coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſellours and with vs all Amen.</p>
               <p>OF late tyme aboute the begynny<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g of this preſente parlyament / that was begonne the thryd day of No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vember in the .xxj. yere of the Reygne of our moſte drad ſoueraygne lorde y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> now is / Kyng henry the yght, defenſor of our feyth / when the clergye hard tell that the greate extorcyon that they had long tyme vſed / in the wrongfull takyng of mortu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aryes / and by probate of teſtamentys / ſhulde be reformed / and more meanely qualyfyed to the greate relyfe and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forte of all the kynges laye ſubyectes / Then one of theym ſtode vp / and ſayde opynly / that it was to be feared that the comons of this realme of Englonde / be mych infected with hereſye bycauſe they intendyd to minyſhe and to plucke from
<pb facs="tcp:26122:2"/> the churche y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lybertyes of Chryſtes chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che / dredyng that thereby it myght for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune to this realme / as lately be fell to the realme of Boeme / that was the ſub<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uercion of that ſame realme / But it ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>myth that therin y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> clarke there opyned his couetous ſtomake / then callynge theyr wrongfull exaccyo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s to be the lyber<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tyes of Chriſtes church / nat conſideryng that there be .ii. lybertyes in the churche / one that is temporall that hath be geuyn by the kyng &amp; by his noble progenytours which may be reſumed by lyke auctoryte And there is an other ſpirytuall lyberty that comyth only from god / that is ſpoke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of .i. Coryn .iij. ſayeng Our lorde is the ſpyryte / and where the ſpyryte of god is / there is lybertye / and that lybertye none Emperoure ne Kyng can ne may take from the churche.</p>
               <p>¶Now although percaſe the ſayde clerk be a famouſe doctor / &amp; precher of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de of god / and be alſo a chaſte man of his body / yet it aperyth euyde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tly by y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſeyeng
<pb facs="tcp:26122:3"/> that he is ſore infected w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Aueryce / which is the ſeruytude and bondage of Idolls and is alſo roote of all euylls / god of his grace amend it in hym and all other / but he wolde nat there ſpeke of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> volupteous conuerſacion / and extorcion / and other abhomynacyo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s of the clergy / that ryſeth of the ſuperfluite of theyr temporall poſſeſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſions / and of the myſuſyng thereof / ney<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of the vſurpacion of theyr temporall dyngnytes and auctorytes / neyther yet of the grete and moſte deteſtable hereſye of ſymonye vſed and longe tyme accuſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med among theym ſelfys / as ſhall be ſayde here after.</p>
               <p>¶And alſo ſythyn that tyme of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> begyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyng of this ſame forſayd preſente par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyamente it hath byn a comon ſayeng of dyuerſe of the clergy / that there were ne<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uer ſo many herytykes in Englond / as be now at this preſent day / yea and alſo dyuerſe of the lay gentlemen lerned in the comon law of this realme / and other folkes beyng of kynred or hauyng offy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces
<pb facs="tcp:26122:3"/>
/ fees or rewardes or belyechere of the clergy / with a counterfett petye / mo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nefully affyrme / and openly ſpeke the<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſame / wherein it ſemyth that they be nat well circumſpect in theyr ſayenges / for onleſe that they be able to name / and to bryng forth thoſe perſons that they ſpeke of / and meane it by / and alſo that they can ſhew theyr opynyons / and can proue them to be heretycall / It ſhulde ells ſeme to be a greate blaſphemy to the Kynges hyghnes / beyng moſte catholyke and chryſtyane defenſor of the feyth And alſo to be an vnnaturall and execrable ſclan<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>der to his moſt honorable counſel / to this his hygh courte of parlyament / and to all this noble and good catholyke realme / wherein is no lytell offence yf it be well conſidered. ¶And yet percaſe in theyr ſo ſayng all though they myſtake the lay fee therein yet regardyng the cler<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gy in theyr ſayd ſayenges / they may for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune to ſay more trewly therin than they be ware of / as ſhalbe ſayd hereafter / 
<pb facs="tcp:26122:4"/> ¶And although the hereſye of dyuerſe of the clergye ſhalbe here ſum what ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken of / yet the good ſorte of good catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyke and vertous clerkes be nat offe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded thereby / for this wryter and compyler / euer hath ſayd / and contynually wyll ſay with ſaynt Auſten / O veneranda ſacer<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dotum dignitas / in quorum manibus dei filius velud in vtero virginis incar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natur / O felices ſacerdotes / ſi ſacerdo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taliter vixeritis. &amp;.c. yet of the voluptu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous and heretycall ſorte of the clergye it may be ſayde in contrary wyſe as thus / O miſera et deteſtanda ſuperborum / cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pidorum / Iracu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dorum / luxuriancium / guloſorum / Inuidorum / accidioſorum / voluptuoſorum &amp; hereticancium ſacerdo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum / animalis &amp; diabolica condicio / in quorum manibus dei filius iterum quan<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tum in vobis eſt) crucifigitur &amp; morti tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditur / et non defensi ſepulcro / <expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:absed"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>sed</ex>
                  </expan> fetido ſterquilinio mittitur / videlicꝪ in ora et cor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pora ſacerdotu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> multiphariis viciis &amp; hereſi plenorum / O infelices ſacerdotes / ſi non
<pb facs="tcp:26122:4" rendition="simple:additions"/> ſacerdotaliter vixeritis / And it is ſayd Diſt. xl. Ca. multi ſunt. &amp;.c. that there be many preſtes / and that there be but few preſtes / many in name and but few indede / and therof reade in aboke called Dextra pars oculi ſacerdotis.</p>
               <p>¶And alſo where ſome men haue lately taken greate ſtudy &amp; pleaſure / to ympung a vertuous Clerke &amp; a good holſom pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cher of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> word of god / ſo eſtemed to be in the opynio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of many good me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> / &amp; alſo dyuer<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſe me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> hath byn ſett w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> theyr talles in theyr handes to wryte &amp; to marke many of his ſayenges in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> pulpit thynkyng therby to confounde / to abiure or to brenne hym / wherein appered greate lacke of good be<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nygnyte / &amp; of charyte / &amp; therby ſemith to appere greate plentye of craftye &amp; e<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>uyoꝰ cruelnes / &amp; alſo ſome me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> wryte agaynſt dyuerſe good catholyke &amp; cryſtyn layme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> / callyng ſome of theym i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> mockage / y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> pacy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fyer &amp; ſome other of them Eua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gelyke bro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ders / &amp; other dyuerſe names at theyr ple<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure / w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>out any louy<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g &amp; frainall ſpryte of
<pb facs="tcp:26122:5"/> good councell / or of charytable or ſecrete reformacyon.</p>
               <p>¶And alſo they haue taken greate ſtudy in confutyng of ſome other mens wry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tynges / which they thought to be erro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neous / and it ſemyth to them to be well<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don ¶But yet percaſe it may be ſayd to ſuche wryters of thoſe thynges which be but tryfles in comparyſon of other great matters that they neuer luſt to ſpeke ne to wryte of / &amp; yet they be greate errours &amp; como<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ly vſed / as Chryſt ſayd to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> phary<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſeys Ipocrytys / Math. xxiij. &amp; Luc. xi. Woo be to you ſcrybys and pharyſeys Ipocrytys / that teche to pay tythy<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ges of Myntys / Rwe / Annes / Cu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>myn / &amp; ſuche other potteherbys / and ye leue vntaught gretter thynges of more grauyte in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>we Iugment / mercy / charyte / and feyth / Theſe thynges (ſayth Chryſt) muſt be done / and the other nat lefte vndone / ſuche blynde guydes ſpytt out a flee or gnatt / and ſwalow the greate Camell / and outwardely ſhew them ſelfys lyke to
<pb facs="tcp:26122:5"/> be Iuſt men / but inwardly they be full of Ipocryſe and of inyquyte / Trewly ye be witneſſys to your ſelfys (ſeyth Chryſt) for ye be the ſonnys of them that haue kylled the prophettys / and ye be (ſayth Chryſt) ſerpentes and y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> broode or ſpaw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne of venemous adders / ¶And Theſe wordes be now here ſpoken and alſo reherſed for cauſes folowyng / for there be farre greater vycys and more deteſta<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ble ſynnys / cuſtomably vſed / contrarye to the law of god / than theſe thynges be<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fore reherſyd / which of neceſſite ought to be wryten and prechyd of / And as yet belefte vnſpoken / vnprechyd / and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wryten of / as of late ſeaſon / As of Irre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gularyte of dyuerſe of the clergy / ſacry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lege by them vſually comytted in myſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendynge the tythynges &amp; oblacions of Chryſtes churche / on freſſhe apparell on them ſelfes / theyr ſeruantes / theyr hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſys / mulys / and wenches / And in theyr coſtely byldynges and repayryng of theyr houſys and the ſuperfluous apparell of
<pb facs="tcp:26122:6"/> the ſame / with Arras and other thynges theyr wyne &amp; pompous plate / The great expencys and coſte in dayntye vytells / The vnlaufull coniuracyons vſed by fre<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rys and other clerkes / The vſuall bre-Kyng of the .iij. eſſencyall vowes of rely<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gyon The dylygent ſtudy of dyuerſe of the clergye in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſleyght of craftye hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyng and ſettynge of dyſe and cardes to theintent to begyle all men that playeth with them as doctor dewys aſe / byſhope prymero / and ſuch other The felonyes and murders oftyntymes conmytted by clerkys Theyr conuiccio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> therof / and theyr acquitall from y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> conuycte pryſone by wyl<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>full periury of .xii. forſworne clerkys / The hauyng &amp; myſuſyng of te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>porall poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſions of the clergy / contrary to the co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maundement of god in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> olde lawe / and contrarye to the example and techyng of Chryſt in the newe lawe of his goſpell / and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trary to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ordynau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of many holy cano<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> decrees / &amp; co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trary to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> wryty<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gꝭ of diuers holy doctors now ſay<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> heue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> / 
<pb facs="tcp:26122:6"/> ¶The vſuall ſymonye of dyuerſe of the clergy / which is mooſt greate and mooſt deteſtable hereſy / as partly ſhalbe ſayde hereafter / Theſe and ſuche other be the greate offenſys agaynſt the law of god / and yet fewe or none of the comoun pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers / do ſpeke agaynſt any of them / ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther yet he nor any of them which hath taken vpon the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to wryte agaynſt y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſayde tryfels beyng worthy to be called but try<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſyls in comparyſon of the ſayd more gre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uos offencys wryte no thyng of the fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſayd greate and greuous offencys in the lawe / nether ons ſterr theyr pennes therto.</p>
               <p>¶Wherfore it ſemyth that it maybe ſayd to dyuerſe of the prechers and to other of the clergy &amp; to ſuch wryters of ſuch leſſe offencys / as Chryſt ſayd to the pharyſeys Ipocrytys Mat. xxiii. woo be to you ſcry<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>bys &amp; pharyſeys Ipocrytys which theche / preche or wryte / of / or agaynſt y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſmaller offe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cys in goddes lawe / &amp; vſe your ſelfes to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mytt y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> greater offe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cys / &amp; ye neyther
<pb facs="tcp:26122:7"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb facs="tcp:26122:7"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb facs="tcp:26122:8"/> vſe to teche / to preche neyther to wryte agaynſt them / which if the great mercye of god / were nat ouer vs / were myche lyke to be the cauſe of ſubuerſion of this noble Realme / and of all other Regio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s where they be vſed / without correccyon God and oure noble Kyng defe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſor of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> fayth a mende it amen.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="chapter">
               <head>¶Of the kynges grete benyngnyte and fauor vſyd alwey toward y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> clergy And of theyr grete preſumpcyon and cruelte ſhewed agaynſt his grace and his lay ſubiectys. Ca. ij.</head>
               <p>¶It is wryten in the holy decrees that yf any man at any tyme after his baptyſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>me / happen to ſlee a pagaue / although it were in his defence / he ſhall neuer be Receyued into holy orders / yf he happe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to take any holye orders / he ſhalbe put from them as it aperyth Diſtinci. .l. de hiis clericis / yet that natwithſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dyng / it hath oftyntymes beſeen that one preſt
<pb facs="tcp:26122:8"/> hath Robbed / and wylfully murdered a good criſten man / yea and ſomtime one preſte hath wylfully Robbed and murde<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>red an other preſte / and theruppon he hath byn attached / indyted / arayned / and conuicted / wheruppo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> / his ordynary hath byn redye at y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> barre and there hath alowed and Receyuyed him for his cler<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke / contrary to the ſayd canons / and thereuppon / he hath byn co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ueyed to the conuycte preſon / and in ſhort tyme ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after / he hath byn acquytt by a queſt of xij. Forſworne clerkes / and after that he hath ſong and ſayde maſſe at his plea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſure and hathe ſeruyd a cure / and hathe ſonge trentalles for ſoulis / contrary to the ordyuauncis of the ſayd canons / And alſo in the ſayd / .l. Dyſtincion / Cap. i. expremiſſis &amp; ſecu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>do / Si lapſus / and other canons there / as Qui igi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur / and Si quis Ep<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>us / And ſi poſt ordi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nacione<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> / and other / ¶It is alſo there ordeyned that if any clerke at any tyme after the Receyuyng of holye orders,
<pb facs="tcp:26122:9"/> happen to fall in ſynne of the fleſſhe / tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he ſhalbe put frome all holy orders / and from mynyſtryng at the Aulter / &amp; that ſame is affermed by ſaynt Gregory. xi. q<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. iii. Ip<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>e liga<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>di / &amp; there p<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>uilegni oino / &amp; ther by ſaynt Auſtyn Rediclin eſt / And ſuche a clerke ons depoſed or diſgradyd ſhall neuer be admytted ageyne to any holye orders / as it aperith Diſt. l. Si / quis / and / qui ſemell / and preſbiteru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> de quo / Suche preſtis haue hadde to myche fauoure here / in this lande / of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Kyng / of his lordys te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>porall / and of all his laye ſubiectis / for godis ſake / and yet they be none of goddis ſeruau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes / as it aperyth in dyuers holy canons Diſt. l. As is beforeſaid / And alſo it aperyth by / chriſtꝭ goſpell Math. vij. that god vtterly Refu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſyth all ſuche clerkys / To be any of his. ſeruauntis / where it aperyth that ſuche clerkys preſomtuouſly ſhall ſaye to god / Lorde, Lorde, haue nat we propheſied &amp; preched in thy name / and in thy name / we haue caſt out deuyles / &amp; in thy name
<pb facs="tcp:26122:9"/> we haue done or made many vertues / And the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Chriſt ſhall knowlege to them / that he neuer knew theym (as to theyre ſaluacion) and wyll bid theym / go ye fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> me all ye ſynners / &amp; workers of i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>yquite. ¶And here ye ſhal ꝑceyue on y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> one ſyde y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> great ſuperfluous fauour heretofore ſhewed to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> clergye, by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Kyng / &amp; by his noble ꝓgenytours / &amp; by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lordes and by other theyr laye ſubiectꝭ / and on y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> other ſyde ye ſhall ꝑceyue the great crueltye / &amp; ꝑcyalyte of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ordynaries &amp; of other Cler<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kys of auctoryte / cuſtumably ſhewed to the Kynge &amp; to his noble ꝓgenytouris / to his lordis &amp; to other his laye ſubiectis / ¶For where Clerkis many tymes by theyr euyll gouernaunce / as by theyr thef<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>te / murder / ſacrilege &amp; other theyr gre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uous offe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cys haue loſte the pryuylege of theyr Clergy / as hath byn ſayd before / by theyr owne law / y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> is by many holy ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nons in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> holy decrees / &amp; by Chriſtis goſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pell / yet y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Kyngꝭ hyghtnes / &amp; his noble ꝓgenytourꝭ y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lordys / &amp; other theyr laye
<pb facs="tcp:26122:10"/> ſubiectis haue alweys ben contented at theyr deſyrys and requeſtys / to make ſtatutys / in fauour of ſuche clerkys mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derers and other / thynkyng thereby / to haue deſerued thanke of god / and of the other good ſorte of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> clergy / where they in recompe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of ſuch reuerence &amp; greate curteſy / and good fauorable humanyte ſhewed to them / haue alweys i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> contrary wyſe ſhewed to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> noble progenytourys of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> kyng / &amp; to his grace / to his lordys temporall / and to all other y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> kynges lay ſubiectys / all cruelty / and cuſtomable per<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cyalyte in ſuche theyr auctorytes as they haue vſyd / ſumetyme preſomtuouſly and cruelly / &amp; few tymes or neuer louyngly / nether fauorably nether yet indyfferent<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly / as now ſhalbe ſayd And fyrſt of theyr preſumpcyon.</p>
               <p>¶Where god by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> mouth of the prophet Eſaye .x. curſyth all them that maketh any wyked lawes / yet the prelatys and other the clergy nat dredyng that curſe haue made ſecretely in theyr conuocacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <pb facs="tcp:26122:10" rendition="simple:additions"/> houſe / here within the Kynges realme preſumtuouſly certeyne conſtituicions that they call prouyncyall / wherein i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſum caſe they ſpare nat to curſe &amp; to e<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>terdyte y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Kynges caſtels royall / &amp; other honora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble his dominyons &amp; all the inhabytau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce therof / how noble / how good / how ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuous / howſyke / and how nygh the arte<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tycle of deth ſo euer they be / as it appreth in the conſtitucions prouynciall in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piter / Contingit aliquando / and all that is done for mayntenaunce of theyr tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porall poſſeſſions and of theyr temporall honourys / where it ſemyth y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> none ſuch ſhulde be longyng to them.</p>
               <p>¶And here now folowith ſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>what more of the cruelte and percyalyte longe tyme ſhewed and contynued by the prelates and other y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Clergy to all y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Kynges laye ſubiectes and of the vnlawfull and par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cyall fauour borne by the ſayd prelatys to the vnthryfty &amp; curſyd ſorte of the clergy In the holy decrees Diſt .l. There is a lytell chapter y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> begynyth thus / Si quis
<pb facs="tcp:26122:11"/> viduam / wherin it is ordeyned that yf a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny man marye a wedow or woman lefte of an other man he ſhall neuer there af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter take any holy orders / and yf he hapen to take any ſuche holy orders he ſhalbe put from them / And in the ſame chapiter it is ordeyned y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> who ſo euer at any tyme after his baptyſme be in dede / or by coun<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſell / or in his defence / gyltye or agreable to any murder / or manſlaughter / he ſhal neuer take holy orders / And yf he hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen to take any then he ſhallbe put from them / and he ſhall neuer take commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> or howſyll but lyke a laye man / And alſo in the nexte chapiter folowyng Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenit ad nos There it is ordeyned that yf any clerke at any tyme after holy or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders by hym taken / fall in lapſe of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> fleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhe he ſhalbe put from all holy orders &amp; he ſhall neuer ſerue at the aulter as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore is ſayd.</p>
               <p>¶Now / no man can rede that euer any lay man hath byn fauoryd or dyſpenſed withall by his ordynary in this caſe / how
<pb facs="tcp:26122:11"/> honeſt / how good / and how vertuous ſo euer he and his wyfe or wyffys were / and yet all his doyng in that caſe / hath be done by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> law of god &amp; of the holy church / wherin the ſayd ordynaryes haue vſyd eyther to hygh Iuſtyce or to greate cruel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te without dyſcrecyon or mercy.</p>
               <p>¶And on y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> other ſyde few men or none can tell or hath redd that euer any of the clergye comytty<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g felony wylfull murder fornycacyo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> adultery inceſte ſacrelege / or tape before takyng of holy orders / or aft takyng of them / hath at any tyme loſt any orders / or y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he hath ben forbodyn or denayed minyſtracio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> at the aulter at any tyme / wherin the prelates hath ſhewed theyr vndyſcrete fauour and great per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cialyte / Therfore it were a charytable dede to make an acte of parlyament that all ſuch vnhappy preſtes whom the holy canons puttyth from mynyſtracyon at y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> aulter / ſhulde at y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> temporall law loſe all maner of benefytes of theyr clergy / and ſhulde dye for felony or morder done by
<pb facs="tcp:26122:12"/> them for they be no clerkys ne ſhall ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer be admyttyd to theyr clergy as before is ſayd. Diſt. .l.</p>
               <p>¶And although diuers prelates may per<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>caſe trewly ſay y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they neuer comytted ne<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ther ſuch preſumptuous rygoure nether ſuche vndyſcrete &amp; ꝑeyall fauour as now hath byn ſpoky<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of / yet they can nat excuſe them ſelfys / but that they know that hyt hath byn ſo this long tyme vſyd / and yet euery one of them ſufferyth it / and ney<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſpeke / neyther preche / neyther yet wryte agaynſt it / wherefor it may be ſayd to them as chryſt ſayd to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> phareſeys Ipo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>crytys Math. xxiij. wo be to you. &amp;.c.</p>
               <p>¶And yet ouer this the ſayd clergy hath made an ordynau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce and decre that who ſo euer teche preche or frowardly menyth contrary to any of the fore ſayd decrees decretallys or ordynaunces in theyr con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitucyons prouyncyall ſhallbe Iugyd an heretyke / as it aperyth in the ſayd con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtytucions ꝓuyncyall titulo / de hereticis Cap. nullus quo<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> / And where the kyng
<pb facs="tcp:26122:12" rendition="simple:additions"/> of his Iuſtyce and gracyous fauour pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claymyth all his Actys made in his hygh courte of parlyamente / in euery ſhere within this his realme / and cauſyth them to be in prynte bycauſe no man ſhulde be excuſyd by ygnoraunte / The clergye doth in a contrary wyſe / make theyr con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtycyons to be ſecrete from / the temporall &amp; lay ſubiectes of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Kyng / whereby they may daylye fall in daunger of hereſye / and that Ignorantly / wherin ſemyth to be myche craftye cruelte</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="chapter">
               <head>¶Of the moſt deteſtable hereſye of ſy<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>monye vſyd cuſtomably by them of the clergy and the moſt co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>uenye<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t order for the punyſhment of the ſame. Cap. iij.</head>
               <p>¶Alſo he that luſteth to rede in the holy decrees. i. .q<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. i. he ſhall there fynde a greater dau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ger amonge the clergy tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> is yet ſpoken of / or moche preched / or wry<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ten of / that is y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> euery Symonyte is an infydele and an heretyke / and that he is
<pb facs="tcp:26122:13"/> no member of Chryſtys church / and that he is ſo curſed that nothyng ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> be bleſſed by hym / And yet moſte comonly they be the gouerners and rulers of the church here in this world / yea and among ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nye ſundry kyndys of hereſyes reherſyd xxiiij. q<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. iij. Quidam aute<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> heretici / That hereſy of ſymony is furſt named as moſt deteſtable before god / yea and it is ſo de<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>teſtable &amp; abhomynable y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> it can nat wel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>be otherwiſe lykoned but to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> treaſon of Iudas y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſolde and betrayed god / yea and yet morouer it is ſo deteſtable before god / that euery man beyng of auctoryte that knowyth it / and is nat vehemently chaufed therwith / &amp; agaynſt y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> offe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ders therin is curſed with Symon Magus / which as clerkys ſay is da<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pned in hell.</p>
               <p>¶What prelate or other clerk of Auctory<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>te / can a voyde now that curſe / that fell on Symon Magus / And alſo y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Clergy tell the lay men / that who ſo euer know any maner of perſon / to be an heretyk and doth nat dyſcloſe that perſon / and
<pb facs="tcp:26122:13"/> alſo his hereſy / he is afauorer of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſy / and he may be thought as gyltye ther<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>in as the pryncypall heretyke / as it ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peryth .xxiij. q<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. iij. Qui poteſt obuiare / &amp; Alſo it is wryten Conſencie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes &amp; agen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes pari pena punientur / And alſo Ioh .ij. Qui dixerit ei aue co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>icat operibꝰ eius malignis Ecce predixi vobis vt in die dn<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>i no<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fundamini / Now than by the Kynges comaundement or aſſente It may be aſked of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Clergy / in theyr houſe of conuocacyon which and how manye of them can trewly ſay / that he neuer co<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mytted that hereſy of ſymony / nether hath conſentyd therto / nether hath at any tyme knowyn one or mo clerkꝭ to ha<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ue offendyd therein / &amp; yet he hath nat dy<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſcloſed it / It is to be thought by veheme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t ſuſpicio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> / y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> fewe of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> can Iuſtely excuſe the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſelfys therof / And yet they be nether attached / impryſoned / examyned / abiu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red / neyther burned therfore But they be alwayes cruel on the Kynges lay ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iectys / in areſtyng the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> / by force / by cruell
<pb facs="tcp:26122:14"/> impryſonyng of theym in theyr Darke and cloſe pryſons / where none of theyr frendes or other good charytable / and catholyke men / can be ſuffred to cum to theym / to ſee theym and to Relyefe the vnholſom diete of theym / with theyr re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſe of a lytell colde meat / ſmall &amp; palled drynke / with honger thurſt / and coulde / with harde lodgyng among vermyn / w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> many ſubtyll and crafty oppoſyngys / &amp; thretinyngꝭ for theyr lucure / yea and in abiuryng or burnyng of theym / which ſu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tyme ſkantely know what good fayth / &amp; hereſye meaneth / ¶The grace of god / and of good Kyng harry amend it / and graunte that the byll of the laye co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mons callyd the byll / ex officio may haue good furtheraunce and ſpede / or ells the cruel<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tye of the clergye is lyke to encreaſe / &amp; nat to be pacyfyed / for it ſemyth that they had as leue dye / as to forgoo any parte of theyr temporall power in ſuche cruell ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>delynge the Kynges laye ſubiectys with the ſworde of vengeaunce and of cruell
<pb facs="tcp:26122:14"/> blodeſhedyng / as it apperyth in theyr aunſwer to the ſayd byll exofficio / alleg<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gyng for theym this text / Non veni mit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tere pacem / <expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:absed"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>sed</ex>
                  </expan> gladiu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> / wherin they ſhew theyr foule Ipocryſye couered with ſa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cti<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>te / And vnder that name and coloure of charyte / they be cruell murderers &amp; blode ſheders / as before is ſayd / It is alſo ſayd that euery good Chyriſtyn man ſhulde rather ſufferdeth than to receyue the ho<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly ſacrament of the handys of anye here<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tycall preeſt knowyngly / as it apereth / xxiiij. q<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. i. Si quis dederit.</p>
               <p>¶Symony is comyttyd thre dyuers wa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ys / furſt by reward of the tonge / as by fla<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>teryng or fayre wordes of requeſt / or cra<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uynge / geuyn by your ſelfe or by any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther perſone for you to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> entente to haue therby ſpu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>all promocyon / ye knowyng it furſt or laſt / are bounde in medyately to reſygnacyon and to reſtytucyon / Se<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>condly by reward of vndewe ſeruyce as when ye or any other perſon for you do
<pb facs="tcp:26122:15"/> ſeruyes / or promyſe ſeruice to any man to thentente to haue ſpyrytuall promocyon / ye that knowyng are bounde to reſtytu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cyon / Thrydly by reward of money or of any thyng that is money worth as yf ye or any perſon for you geue or ꝓmyſe any ſume of mony any catell or ferme any ſtuffe of houſholde or any other thynge that is money worth / as ſone as ye may haue knowlege therof / ye are bounde to reſygnacyon and to reſtytucyon of all your profytes before reſeyuyd therof / as it appreth .i. q<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. iii. Saluator predicit / and alſo i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> deſtructorio vico<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abrum"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>rum</ex>
                  </expan> in the tytle and chapyter of Symony.</p>
               <p>¶It hath byn oftentymes knowen to many men that dyuers Clerkes haue comytted and vſyd this hereſye of ſymo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nye / But it hath nat byn myche knowyn that any of them hath truly repentyd the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> therof / nether by fre reſygnacyon / of theyr benefyces ſo ſymonytely gotyn / ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther yet by reſtytucyon of theyr temporall goodes ſimonytely and heretically gote<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> / 
<pb facs="tcp:26122:15"/> nether in theyr teſtame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes at the poynte of deth / wherfore it is to be ſuppoſed and is myche to be fered / that all ſuche here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tycall clerkys haue lacked / and ſhall lack grace of trew repe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>taunce / and of ſatyſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faccion / In confyrmacyon whereof / it is nat redd / y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> balam / of whom it is wry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten Nu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. xxii. and deut .xxiiij. nether of Geyſye of whom .iiij. regum. v. nether of Iudas y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> traytour of who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Mat. xxvi. neyther of the fals Byſhoppys ſcrybes &amp; phareſeys Ipocritꝭ / which bought Chriſt of Iudas / of whom in many placys of ho<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly ſcrypture nether of Symon Magus of who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Actu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. viij. All whiche were ſymo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nytys / byyng or ſellyng ſpu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>all thy<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ges for te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>porall rewarde / of who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> it is nat fownd that euer any of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> dyd frutefull pena<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce but by all lykelyhod / they dyed Impeny<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tente / and out of the ſtate of grace / And here ye may marke a meruelous vſurpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cion in the pope / for where ſaynt Peter neuer dyd / ne wolde aſſoyle Symon Magus of that deteſtable cryme and
<pb facs="tcp:26122:16"/> hereſye of Symony / but ſuffered hym to peryſh both in body and in ſoule / yet the pope hath vſyd to aſſoyle all ſymonyte clerkes for money / yea and alſo to dyſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pence with them / and to lycence them contynually for terme of theyr lyues / to retayne and enioye the benefycys and all the frutys and profytes of the ſame ſymonytly and heretycally gotten / with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out ſcrupuloſyte of conſcyence.</p>
               <p>¶And yet the pope and the clergye wyll nat be contented / that the Kyngys hygh<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nes ſhall at any tyme perdone the lyfe of any lay heretycall perſone / that they haue onys Iuged to the fyer or haue put from them to the lay handes / although it be euydently knowen / that the kyng hath more power ouer the bodyes of his ſubiectes / than the pope and all his cler<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gye hath / where by it ſhulde ſeme that the pope is nat only an heretyke hym ſelfe / but alſo a cuſtomable maynteyner and vpholder of heretykes and hereſies And yet herof we can here no prechyng
<pb facs="tcp:26122:16"/> nether ſee no wrytyng of late ſeſon / but ſome one hath ſcornefully ſayd / I pray you be good to the clergye / wherefore it may be ſayde to many of the prechers / and to ſuch wryters and confuters of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſmaller hereſyes / that leuyth the greter offencys in goddys lawe as the ſayde ſymonycall hereſyes and other be / to be vnprechyd / vnwrytyn and nat co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>futed / as Chriſt ſayd to the phareſeys Ipocrytꝭ Math. xxiii. as before is wryten / wo be to you. &amp;.c.</p>
               <p>¶The correccion of all ſuche enormytes in the clergye of this realme be longyth to the kynges hyghnes as to his ſeculer-power / as it aperyth by dyuerſe holy ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nons y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> is .xxiii. q<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. i. Si apud carnales. xxiii. q<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. iii. Qui po<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t. xxiii. q<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. v. Sunt que da<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> enormia / and there de lyguribus &amp; ve<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ne ticis / and there Regum officium eſt &amp; ther / Qui malos ꝑcutit / and there Si ꝓpterea / and in manye other dyuerſe placis of the holy decrees.</p>
               <p>¶And euery man both temporall and
<pb facs="tcp:26122:17"/> ſpu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>all is bownde to be obedyent and to beleue in all the holye canons / and to maynteyn / nothing contrary to any of theym vppon payne of hereſye as it is ſayd and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maunded in the ſayd co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cions ꝓuyncyall / Titulo de hereticꝭ Ca. Nullus quo<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> and alſo .xxv. q<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. i. viola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tores canonum / ¶And in co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fyrmacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the Kynges Auctoryte for correccion of all enormytees in the Clergye / ye may harkyn what is ſayd therof Ioh. xix. Whan Chriſt ſtode before Pylate and was there vntrewly accuſed of treſon agaynſt Ceſar / there Pylate ſayd to Chriſt / knoweſt nat thou that I haue power to crucyfye y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> / and alſo to dyſchar<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ge and to forgyue the / Chryſt denayed it nat / but affermed it / ſaying / Thou ſhul<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>deſt haue no power vppon me, but yf it had be geuyn the from aboue / as from god / Harkyn alſo ſaynt Paule Ro. xiii. Wher he wylleth euery man to be obedi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ent to the hygh power of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Kyng ſeying lett euery man be ſubiect to the powers / 
<pb facs="tcp:26122:17"/> There is no power but of god / he that reſyſteth power / doth reſyſt y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ordynaun<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ce of god / And they that ſo reſyſte gere dampnacion to theym ſelfys / for pryncis be nat ſett here in drede of anye good warke / but of euyll &amp;.c. He berith the ſword nat without cauſe / he is goddys mynyſtre and auenger wrathfullye to hym that euyll doth. &amp;c.</p>
               <p>And ſaynt Peter. i. Petri. ii. ſayth Be ye ſubiect to euery humayne creature for god &amp;.c. to the vengeaunce of euyll doers and to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> laude and prayſe of good men. &amp;.c.</p>
               <p>¶The prechyng / wrytyng / &amp; ſhewyng of theyſe forſayd and other great and greuous offe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſys agaynſt y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lawe of god / And the declaracio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Kynges power in punyſſhyng therof / had byn and yet wylbe moche pleſant to god / And alſo it ſhuld haue bene good acceptable ſeruice to the Kynges hyghnes / for it ſhulde haue put / and yet may put his grace in good perfyte knowledge / what belo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gyth
<pb facs="tcp:26122:18"/> for a Kyng or prynce to do herafter in all ſuche outrageous offe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſis / yf y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Clergye / do nat ceaſe ther of / And ſo the correcion thereof had byn / and yet may be a helpe &amp; furtheraunce to the mayneteynau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of the Kynges honour / and of his preroga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyfe reyall / For by eſtymacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the knowle<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ge therof hathe byn longe tyme kepte from his grace / and from his noble pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>genytours / and from y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> temperall lordes peeris of this Realme / wherfore in the honoure of god and for the dewtye that ye owe to the Kyng / ye prechers &amp; wry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters that haue herto fore prechyd / and wryten / of ſuche tryfyls and ſmaller of fenſys in godys lawe as is before reher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed / Now preche ye and wryte ye furſte in reprouyng and oppreſſyng of theſe for ſayde greate and deteſtable vycys / and that done than may ye preche and wryte of other ſmaller offencys at your plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure (quia ipſa oportet facere &amp; illa non omittere) And ſo ye maye alſo a voyde fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> your ſelfys y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> greate &amp; perelous curſe
<pb facs="tcp:26122:18"/> that is fallen on Symon Magus / or els the foreſayde holy canon. i. q<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. i. quis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quis per pecuniam / reporteth that ye be in greate daunger therof / And in ſo do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yng / the tyme ſhalbe well ſpente / and god and the Kynge ſhalbe well ſeruyd / and the comynaltye of this realme may be therby ſett at moche reſt and peace / ¶For the clergye in theyr cruell perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cyon of the kynges laye ſubiectes do all contrarye to Chryſtes doynges and to his comaundementes and alſo contrary to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> holy canon. xxiiij. q<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. iii. Cap. vltimo in which holy cano<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> is reherſed Chryſtes acte and comaundement Math. xiij. Seyeng / ſuffyr ye as well the cokell as the good corne to growe bothe to gether tyll haruyſt tyme / for drede that when ye wolde wede and plucke vp the cokell ye ſhall alſo therwith plucke vp the goode corne by the rote / And there the ſayde holy canon ſeyth It is neceſſarye that ſome hereſyes &amp; heretykes be / And alſo Math. xv. where Chryſtis appoſtolys
<pb facs="tcp:26122:19"/> ſayd to hym / Thou knowyſt that in this thy worde the pharyſeys be ſklanderyd / And there Chryſt bade &amp; comaunded tho<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſe pharyſeys to be ſuffred / ſeyyng they were blynde and leders of blynde men or of blynde thynges / And no clerk dow<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tyth but knowyth thoſe pharyſees to be heretykes / and yet Chryſt bade ſuffer them / But y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſayd cruell ſorte of the Cler<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gye hath nat of late ſeaſon done ſo / But ſome tyme it hath ben thought that they wold abiure a good cryſtyan man cauſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les / as yt ſemyth by ſome perſons lately beyng in theyr daunger &amp; priſon / where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore theſe premyſſys well conſydered it ſhulde ſeme to be very neceſſarye coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell to the ordynaryes ſpu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>all and to other the Clergye / to aduyſe the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> / to leue theyre cruell handelyng of the kynges lay ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iectes for ſuch hereſyes as be but ſmall hereſyes in comparyſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of greter / tyl they may clere and clenſe theym ſelfys from ſymonye that is the greteſt and moſte ab<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>homynable hereſye or ells tyll they can
<pb facs="tcp:26122:19"/> proue by good auctoryte that ſymony is none hereſye / for it ſemyth to be agreat abuſe that where a prelates dewtye is to fede Chryſtes flocke that is put to his kepyng with holſom doctryne / yea and to anoynte and to hele them that be in<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fected or ſcabbed / louyngly with ſofte ſal<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nys / and nat to bete them / nether to ſhere or poll them / nether to ſlee theym in there good name / ne other wyſe / but louyngly and ſecretely to reforme them that be in errours / lyke a good ſhepherd and nat to be amonge them lyke awolfe or lyke a bere / that all weyes fedyth hym<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſelfe on y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> flocke / and neuer chereſſheth them / for to ſuche one it may wel be ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de ye Ipocryte and archeherytyke / yf ye luſt to pyke a ſtrawe or mote out of myne eye / furſte it wylbe myche neceſſary / that ye drawe out the greate poſte or beame from your owne eye / and ſo ſhall ye the better ſee to pyke the ſtrawe or more out of myne eye.</p>
               <p>¶And yf y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Clergye wyll nat be therew<hi rend="sup">t</hi>
                  <pb facs="tcp:26122:20"/> contented / then it is to be thought that the kynges hyghnes hathe good cauſe to ſay to them / as Chryſt ſayd to the ſcrybys and pharyſeys Ipocrytes as is before ſayd Math. .xxiii. ye be wytteneſſys to your owne ſelfys for ye haue wryten in your byll of anſwere / to the byll of com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>playnte that my lay ſubiectes hath put to me in theyr ſupplycacyon agaynſt you y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſpu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>all ordynaryes of this my realme / cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led the byll ex officio / that ye were neuer greuous to your bretherne / and goſtly chylderne but onely to ſuche as were in<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fected with the peſtelent poyſon of here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſye / with whom (ye ſaye) that ye are co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maunded by Chryſtes goſpell to haue no peace ſayenge. Math. x. Non veni mit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tere pacem <expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:absed"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>sed</ex>
                  </expan> gladiu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> / And although yet as it ſemyth by the proſeſe of that chapy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter / it is nat in tended nether mente as ye haue applyed yt / for in foure or fyue hundered placys of ſcrypture / god hath comaunded loue &amp; peace / and nat ſtryfe warre / nether blod ſhedy<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g / And therfor
<pb facs="tcp:26122:20"/> it aperyth that it may be Iuſtely ſayd to you as Chryſt ſayd to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> pharyſeis Ipocry<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tes in the foreſayd goſpell Math. xxiii. ye be the ſonnes of them that ſlewe the prophetys / ye wyll ſay ſeyth Chryſt that yf ye hadd byn offycers in that tyme whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> your fathers ſlew the prohetꝭ that ye wolde nat haue byn theyr felowes in blode ſhedyng / but it is nat ſo / for at this day ye ſay ye loue your brothers / and yet ye wyll kyll them / but ye ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> nat do both / and therfore Chryſt calleth you in that ſayde goſpell / the ſpawne or ſeede of ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemous Adders and ye wolde blynde the people and ſay that therin ye eſteme that ye do acceptable ſeruyce to god in all ſuche your craftye cruelte / but ye know the contrarye / though ye luſt to applye and to expounde holye ſcrypture at your pleaſure and to your wretched and ſyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full appetytis / to colour and to hyde your cruelty and your Ipocryſye / And yf any of my lay ſubietꝭ ſhew to you holy ſcryp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture ſuffycyent to confou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de your wrong
<pb facs="tcp:26122:21"/> applynge of ſcrypture / and your Iwyſh fables / Anon ye ſay that no lay man ſhulde medell with holy ſcrypture / but therin Chryſt co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>foundeth you / Luc. .xi. ſayeng to you of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> clergy wo be to you y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> be lerned in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lawe / y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> haue taken or bor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ne away y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> kaye of cu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nynge / &amp; your ſelfe haue nat e<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tred or gone i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> / &amp; ye haue forbo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den thoſe y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> e<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tred / &amp; hereby ye thynke to coloure &amp; to hyde your greate cruell Ipo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cryſy / but it is wryte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> by a famous doctor in a boke called Deſtructoriu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> victoru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> / That by dyuers wayes a ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> may know an Ipocrite / wherof one now folowyth / ¶Ccognoſeuntur ipocrite ex opp<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſſione bono<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abrum"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>rum</ex>
                  </expan> / Opprimunt enim bonos ꝑſeque<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> do factis / &amp; detrahe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>do verbis / cuiuſmo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>di uide<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abur"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>ur</ex>
                  </expan> eſſe hoe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s multi ſuꝑiores <abbr>eccle</abbr> 
                  <abbr>ta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſeclares</abbr> 
                  <expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abquam"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>quam</ex>
                  </expan> regulares / qui fideles &amp; humi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les ſeruos xp<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>i perſequ<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tur / id eſt eos incar<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cera<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>do &amp; aliqua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>do combure<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>do occidu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t / <expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:absed"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>sed</ex>
                  </expan>, quare hoc faciunt / Certe experientia do cente / pro eo ꝙ eorum vitam reꝓbant voluptuoſam / &amp; negligenciam reprehen<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dunt
<pb facs="tcp:26122:21"/>
/ SꝪ o miſer qui taliter agis / quare reſpiciendo ſcripturas ſacras / &amp; ſpeciali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter euangelia / non conſideras / ꝙ i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> aug mentacionem ſue proprie dampnacionis ita fecerunt predeceſſores tui pontifices falſi / ſcribe &amp; phareſei / qui de bonis ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſie voluptuoſe vixeru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t / ſicut tu nunc Nonne ep<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>i occiderunt rp<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>m / <abbr>aplos</abbr> &amp; ſco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s martires / reputando eos hereticos ꝓeo ꝙ eorum pecca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> reꝓbauerunt / ſic tu repu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tas eos hereticos qui tuam vitam repro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bant voluptuoſam. &amp;.c.</p>
               <p>¶Now ſythens it is ſuffycyently layde and prouyd to you by dyuerſe greate auc<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>torytees of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> holy lawe canon / that cler<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>kes ſymonytes be gretteſt heretykes / yea and archeheretykes in co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>paryſon of a lay man that is an heretyke / and ſy<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>thens alſo that the ſame holy law canon affermyth and declareth euery man of auctoryte that is nat vehemently chafyd and dyſpleſed with you for y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſame your ſymony / and hereſye / to be curſed with Symon Magus which all ye wyll gra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>te
<pb facs="tcp:26122:22"/> and afferme to be dampned in to hell per<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>petually / And alſo ſythens it is ſufficie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tly prouyd by holy ſcrypture and alſo it is de<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>creed by dyuers of the ſayd holy canons before alleged / that the punyſſhme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t ther<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>of belongyth to me that am your kynge &amp; gouernour / as to our ſeculer power / what ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ye now ſay but y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> of very Iuſtice in goddys cauſe and in eſchewyng / and avoydyng of that terryble curſe y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> fell on Symon magus / from which almyghtye god of his great mercy ſaue and defende vs / wee muſte be vehementley ſterede and chaufed agaynſte you / and accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dyng to your demeritis / and to your for ſayd aunſwere to the ſayd byll ex officio / to haue no peace with you / and to ſay to you with criſte / Math. x. Non veni<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mittere pacem <expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:absed"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>sed</ex>
                  </expan> Gladium / for heryn ye be wytteneſſis to your owne ſelfis / And ſo of neceſſite we muſt ſe you punyſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed with the ſworde of ſharpe execucio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> / as ye haue cauſed other ſmall heretykys beyng but ſmall in co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>paryſon of them y<hi rend="sup">t</hi>
                  <pb facs="tcp:26122:22"/> be gretter heretykes of late tyme to be punyſſhed / as with cruell areſtyng you / harde impreſonyng opynlye abiuryng you / and greuouſly amerſyng you with great fynys / and with takyng from you / all that ye haue here / before ſymonytely and heretycally goten / and longe recey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued / or elles with fyer conſume you / yf ye luſte nat to abiure / for in this caſe ye be wyttneſſys to your ſelfys as before is ſayd ¶And it is congruent / and well conſonant and agreable to good reaſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> / and to all lawes of god and of man / furſt to punyſſhe / and to confownde the greatter offenders / and archeretykys / and afterwarde the leſſe / for euery byſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop and preeſt heretyk maye trewly be called an Archeherytyke in comparyſon of a laye heretyke / aſwell for the qualy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tees and dyfference of theyr ſpu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>all dyg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyte / as of theyr offenſys / and therfore it ought aſwell to be furſt punyſſhed / as alſo moſt greuouſly / and moſt openly pu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nyſſhed / wytnes of ſaynt Bar. ſayyng / 
<pb facs="tcp:26122:23"/> Non enim par debet eſſe pena / vbi diſpar<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>eſt cauſa.</p>
               <p>¶Nowe yf any clerke luſt to make an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer here to / then for the loue of god lett theyr aunſwere be put in wrytyng chary<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tably / that it may be Replyed to / yf nede be / Or elles lett theym yelde theym ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fys gyltye therin / and put theym ſelfys holye to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> mercye &amp; grace of the Kynges hyghnes / whiche is / and hath alweys ben / mercyfull and gracyous / </p>
               <q>
                  <pb facs="tcp:26122:23"/>
                  <list>
                     <item>¶Viuat Rex</item>
                     <item>Gaudeat grex</item>
                     <item>Luceat lex</item>
                  </list> In Regno maieſtatis.</q>
               <q>
                  <list>
                     <item>¶Salus ſeniori<expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abbus"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>bus</ex>
                        </expan>
                     </item>
                     <item>Concors coi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                        <expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abbus"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>bus</ex>
                        </expan>
                     </item>
                     <item>Et pax hoi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                        <expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abbus"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>bus</ex>
                        </expan>
                     </item>
                  </list> Bone volu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tatis.</q>
            </div>
            <closer>¶Amen amen ſey euery man.</closer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="colophon">
            <p>¶Impreſſum / Cum priuilegio regali.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <pb facs="tcp:26122:24"/>
            <head>¶Tabula.</head>
            <list>
               <item>¶How ſome of the Clergy and theyr adherentis cauſeles haue ſkla<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>derouſe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly ſpoken agayns this noble realme of Englande and agayns dyuers of the Kynges lay ſubiectes / and haue prechyd &amp; wryten agaynſt ſmall offe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſys / leuy<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> greter offenſys agaynſt the law of god vntouched. Ca. .i.</item>
               <item>¶Of the kynges grete benyngnyte and fauor vſyd alwy to ward y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> clergy And of theyr grete preſumpcyon and cruelte ſhewed agaynſt his grace and his lay ſubiectys. Ca. .ij.</item>
               <item>¶Of the moſt deteſtable hereſy of ſy<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mony vſyd cuſtomably by them of the clergy and the moſt co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>uenye<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t order for the punyſhment of the ſame. Ca. iij.</item>
            </list>
            <trailer>¶Finis.</trailer>
         </div>
         <div type="colophon">
            <pb facs="tcp:26122:24"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:26122:25"/>
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>printer's device of John Skot</figDesc>
                  <head>ALAVENTVRE · TOVT VIENT APONIT QVI PEVT · ATENORE IOHN SKOT ·</head>
                  <p>I S</p>
                  <p>S K</p>
               </figure>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:26122:25"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
